Aloy.
Survive.
She is dying!
To take her there is blasphemy!
She should be near her mother!
Aloy, I'm so sorry.
Turn your face to the sun, child.
Rost.
No. No, no, no, no.
I have to get out of here.
i need my focus, now.
They … they must have found me before I
bled out.
But why is no one here? Where am I?
My clothes, good.
But where's my focus?
It's here, okay.
Am I inside the sacred mountain?
But only Matriarchs are allowed inside.
I … I don't see my bow here.
Or that damaged focus. The one I took off that killer.
Where are they?
I'm picking up some kind of signal.
It must be the damaged focus.
The one I took from that killer.
It's close.
Looks like the ruins I fell into when I was young.
The Nora didn't build this place, the Old Ones did.
But why?
There! With the rest of my things.
Now, what can you show me?
All commanders: halt excavations and proceed
at once to the mission point.
Avoid all contact with Nora savages.
But if you are seen kill every witness.
Target imaging attached. Do not fail.
"Target imaging"?
"Who says I'm like other Nora?"
They saw me through Olin's focus.
How is that possible?
"Better make it quick, I'm heading in."
"Hold for Identiscan."
"You need to stop listening to Ted,
and start listening to me."
Where is this from? And when?
Are you my mother?
Why try to kill me just because I look like you?
[in the distance]
Aloy!
Aloy, you are awake!
You brought me here?
Quickly, you must follow.
To where?
To the place where you were born.
Are you saying I was born here, inside the mountain?
It is easier if I show you.
Why did you bring me here?
It seemed you were dying,
and to die near one's mother is sacred.
Lansra fought it of course, but Jezza sided with me.
Is my mother here?
Am I going to meet her?
It's complicated please just follow me.
Does my mother look like me, but with short hair?
I don't see how that could be.
You were not born of a woman, Aloy.
The mountain is your mother.
What? What are you talking about?
Come.
What is this place?
The great chamber where All-Mother slew the Metal Devil,
and gave birth to you.
Aloy, the Proving massacre was just the first of many disasters.
The war party we sent after the killers was ambushed and slaughtered.
But what does that have to do with where I was born?
My hope is… everything.
This is where we found you.
We heard your cries, came to look, and there you were.
Just … just lying there?
Yes!
You mean I came from behind the door?
Always that is what I have believed.
That you came from the womb of the mountain.
A gift from All-Mother herself.
But others, like Lansra, feared that a darker power put you here.
Not a gift, but a curse.
But this isn't a goddess.
Aloy!
It's a door … with people behind it.
My mother?
Hold for Identiscan.
The Goddess speaks!
Just like the woman I saw.
Error. Alpha Registry corrupted.
Identity cannot be confirmed. Entry denied.
No, no...
Please!
Aloy, All-Mother spoke to you as if She knew you.
Were you not listening?
It didn't recognize me.
Because of corruption! The Goddess's own words.
Surely if you heal this corruption She will see you clearly.
And how would I do that?
You said you've had visions of a woman with short hair.
The killers came for me because I look like her.
But their power is overwhelming!
Is there no other trail to follow?
Olin. He was one of the outsiders the night before the Proving.
The killers saw me through his eyes.
He lives in Meridian.
So you will have to leave the Sacred Land.
I've been an outcast all my life.
Why not an exile too?
Shh, there is another way.
Come and we will make it so.
You said the tribe is on the brink of extinction.
What happened?
After the massacre at the Proving,
a great war party was sent after the killers.
Less than half survived.
How was the war party defeated?
The killers do not fight alone.
Somehow they have a power over the machines,
corrupting them, driving them mad.
So the killers got away?
Yes, and now the only plan my sister Matriarchs can agree to…
…is to sing the Hymn of Atonement
and beg for All-Mother's mercy.
As though She would not want us to help ourselves!
Then what's your plan?
This. This was my plan.
To show you where you were born and loose you
to follow the destiny All-Mother intended for you.
The other High Matriarchs are waiting for us.
Let me do the talking.
Sisters, the Goddess spoke to Aloy.
Told her to heal the corruption.
Ha!
But how is she to do that?
She will have to journey beyond our Sacred Land.
A Seeker?
If the Goddess spoke it must be so.
You would name this thing a seeker?
Sister!
For once, Lansra, join with us!
Pff! This will be your sin not mine.
Send her seeking and may she never be seen again.
Aloy, by the holy grace of the one Goddess,
we hereby anoint you a Seeker of the Nora Tribe.
No barrier can now stay you from your sacred task.
May All-Mother protect you and sustain you.
Stay true.
I will make ready for the hymn.
Our hopes lie with you.
Teersa, what's a Seeker?
You are.
And here is your mark.
In times of great need the High Matriarchs may anoint a Seeker.
A worthy Brave sent forth to accomplish a great purpose.
No matter where that purpose might take her.
Even beyond the borders of the Sacred Land?
Yes. And with the right to return when you are
done.
Or as the need arises.
So I can go anywhere at all? No restrictions?
Even to forbidden places,
like the tainted lands beyond All-Mother's sight.
Or the ruins of the Metal World.
Why are the ruins of the Metal World forbidden?
They are blighted places Aloy.
Dark and wicked, like the children of metal who built them.
When they rebelled and tried to murder All-Mother,
Her wrath leveled their cities but could not cleanse their sin.
Their ancient spite haunts those ruins.
Ready to ensnare anyone foolish enough to enter them.
But I've been in a ruin.
It looked a lot like the inside of All-Mother.
This is something beyond my understanding.
I will trust you to reveal the truth.
Why are the lands beyond Nora territory called tainted?
Is it not obvious?
Our land is sacred.
We live in sight of the one Goddess,
All-Mother, source of all that lives.
Beyond Her sight lies a vast fallen land, spiritually tainted.
That is why it is against tribal law to leave.
But the Seeker blessing will protect you.
So many have suffered.
Is there anything I can do to help?
What is most important is for you
to fulfil the purpose All-Mother has intended for you.
I don't know what that means any more than you do.
Then you must find out.
Have there been other Seekers?
There have, but they are rare,
and most who set out are never heard from again.
Was Rost a Seeker?
No…
Not a Seeker.
What are you not telling me?
This is not the time, Aloy.
What was done with Rost's body?
I'm afraid there was very little left to recover.
But what there was,
we buried at the place where he raised you.
With flowers on the grave.
Thank you.
From here you must go to the gates of the Embrace.
Speak to Varl and he will point the way to Meridian.
If any Nora tries to stand in your way Aloy,
make sure they know you are a Seeker.
Oh I will.
Thank you Teersa, for all you've done.
May All-Mother bless you and watch over you.
[in the distance]
Nora faithful, we will soon begin.
Purify your hearts.
[in the distance]
Soon we will beg forgiveness for the sins that brought such misery on the tribe.
When we hear the Matriarchs lift their voices,
[in the distance]
we will join ours to theirs.
[passerby]
The motherless girl, back on her feet!
The Outcast girl! So she survived her wounds.
[passerby]
She saved many lives. The tribe is lucky to have her.
[in the distance]
Aloy!
Teb?
All-Mother be praised!
I'm so glad to know you're all right.
I heard the rumors but I didn't know for sure
until I saw you just now.
And you're even wearing the tunic I stitched for you.
I'm honoured.
What sort of rumours did you hear?
That you were wounded, expected to die.
And then High Matriarch Teersa insisted
that you be allowed to heal inside All-Mother.
Huh, that caused a stir.
Only Matriarchs are allowed to enter the mountain, but…
…you deserve the honour.
The survivors had told everyone how you fought to save them.
I wasn't the only one to fight.
No, they spoke of Bast and Vala too.
And rost, the man who raised me.
He fought to save me and he died for it.
The survivors didn't speak of him, but I remember him.
He was there that day when you saved
me.
I remember, he stepped in front of you
when my father started yelling.
If, by dying, he saved your life Aloy.
I don't think he regretted it.
What are you doing here with a bow and spear, Teb?
You're a Stitcher not a Brave.
Most of our Braves are dead or wounded, Aloy.
Someone has to defend Mother's Watch.
So I thought i'd help out.
I should be okay, just as long as
I don't try to run any Brave Trails, right?
I need the gate opened.
Do you have any idea how dangerous it is out there?
Are the killers still there?
No, they're long gone.
The war party went after them.
But the killers slaughtered them.
They have some evil power over the machines.
They corrupt them, make them fight at their side.
And these corrupted machines, they're loose in the embrace?
Some have broken through.
And from what I hear it's even worse outside the Embrace.
Believe me this is no time to go traveling.
I need to pass through.
You'll have to talk to Resh then, up on the wall.
He's the new War-Chief. I'm not sure he'll help you.
Why wouldn't Resh help me?
Well, he says…
…mean things about you.
That I'm a motherless curse? An outcast? That sort of thing?
Yeah.
I should be on my way Teb.
May All-Mother go with you.
Ah, the outcast approaches.
Ignore her, continue
the report.
There are rumours of a demon loose in the embrace.
A thing of dark metal that corrupts every machine it touches.
Where did it come from?
They say it broke through the gates of the Embrace.
Who is they?
Varl and his followers.
They tried to stop it but the demon was too fast, too powerful.
Varl's a fool to defend that gate.
It is here at Mother's Watch that we will make our stand.
So far eight groups have arrived from Mother's Heart
to join the Hymn of Atonement, and more are on the way.
Good. All true Nora will lift their voices in song.
Uh, she's still here.
I don't care.
I need the gate opened.
Since when has any outcast's need been my concern?
I recognise you from the Proving.
You saw Bast shatter my trophy and you did nothing.
You would speak ill of the dead? Truly you have no shame.
I nearly put an arrow through your eye.
And you threaten me in front of witnesses?
When the High Matriarchs hear of this
you'll be an outcast all over again.
I've been anointed a Seeker, so open the gate!
You, a Seeker? Have Teersa and Jezza gone insane?
Bad enough that they let you run in the Proving.
But to nurse you back to health inside the sacred mountain?
If you think Teersa and Jeeza are traitors,
why don't you head up the mountain and say that to their faces?
Or do you only talk big when your superiors aren't around?
No wonder a curse is upon us
and children lie dead under cairns of stone.
How can you be so heartless?
I fought beside those children shoulder to shoulder and back to back.
I saw them fall!
If even one of them had been true Nora,
they would have put an arrow in your back.
Resh, come on.
Silence!
Where were you when those
children were being slaughtered?
Or the war party ambushed?
Guarding your little gate here?
I am the Nora War-Chief and this gate is Mother's Watch!
And I am a Seeker anointed by the High Matriarchs!
So open the gate and I will be on my way.
The sooner you're gone from here the better.
What was that?
The demon!
Sound the alarm!
[gong]
By the Goddess! What's it doing to them?
Taking control.
Brace yourselves!
What have you brought on us now, you motherless curse?
Kill them Braves! Kill them all!
[in the distance]
Braves! Ready yourselves!
Today we fight a curse! A demon!
[in the distance]
All-Mother give us strength!
Won't be long.
Gotta get in position.
It's down!
How does it possess other machines?
What's its secret?
How does a machine like that take control of all those Striders?
One of these things marched with the killers at the Proving.
How'd you do it? Show me.
You made them obey you, how?
This, you did it with this.
It's connecting to my Focus!
Then I could use this?
It's worth a shot.
Couple loops of wire, looks like it'll hold.
I just need to test it.
Aloy, how did you do that?
You killed that demon, pulled its guts from the carcass.
The way it controls other machines.
I think i figured it out, but I need to test it on a machine.
Uh, plenty of Striders along the path to the gates of the Embrace I guess.
Exactly! And the gates are where I'll be headed anyway.
I need to speak to Varl.
I always knew you were different Aloy, but…
"But" what?
I think you're a blessing from All-Mother.
No matter what Resh says.
Thank you, Teb.
But I have to go now.
I know you do and my thoughts go with you.
[in the distance]
Braves! I want that gate repaired immediately!
I don't care if you have to bandage it together, get it done.
[in the distance]
They say she fought beside Bast and Vala.
I need to test this device, see what it can do.
Home. To you think he built all this alone.
So many memories.
It's not home anymore, not without Rost.
There's nothing for me here anymore.
Rost, I couldn't leave the Sacred Land without visiting you.
When you said goodbye…
…I told you I'd find you,
track you down.
Well, looks like you did it after all.
Went somewhere I can't follow
I should have known you'd be watching,
At the Proving, looking out for me.
There for me when no one else was.
Like always.
One last time. Thank you Rost.
I won't waste what you've given me, I promise.
I'll make you proud.
I've been…
…trying to puzzle it out but nothing makes sense.
The killers came after me because I look like this…
…a woman. Older, with short hair.
But why, and what's the connection?
If she's my mother then she didn't look Nora.
But if she lives inside the mountain
how could the killers know about her?
The more I learn the less I understand.
I need to track down Olin, an outsider.
He was at the festival the night before the Proving.
Somehow the killers saw me through his Focus.
And he knew it. He could have warned me.
When I find him, well, he's gonna tell me everything he knows.
And he's gonna pay.
All right it's, uh, it's time to leave the Embrace.
I'll try to come back when I can.
Ouch!
Striders. I can test the override device on them.
Should go in quiet.
Didn't go through all of this
to wind up trampled by a frightened herd.
[whistle]
Nice and quiet.
Alright, here it goes!
Come on, come on…
It worked!
It's not hostile.
It seems almost tame.
I think I could ride it.
There we go, attaboy!
That's more like it.
Yah! Yah, yah!
Ride!
This Strider is fast!
This beats walking!
I should try overriding other kinds of machines.
Probably can't ride them all,
but I might find a use for them.
Sounds of fighting just outside the gates?
The gates look shattered.
[in the distance]
Watch yourselves! Bring it closer! Closer!
Varl, I take it?
Am I seeing things…
…or were you riding that Strider when you came through the gate?
Uh, I was. It's hard to explain.
I imagine so.
Strange times we live in, we who've survived.
I recognise you of course.
Aloy, the outcast who won the Proving.
I'm glad to see you survived your wounds.
How did you know that?
I spoke to survivors. They say you fought bravely.
As did Bast.
And my sister.
Your sister was Vala?
I'm very sorry.
Thank you.
She died saving others. There is no better death.
High Matriarch Teersa said you might know the way to Meridian.
The capital of the Carja Sundom?
You seek exile?
No, a traitor named Olin.
The Matriarchs made me a Seeker so I could go after him.
Then you should head north to Mother's Crown.
If you make it, talk to Marea, she'll point the way.
If I make it?
The trail is dangerous.
Ever since the War Party massacre our lands go unpatrolled
and our borders unguarded.
We have no War-Chief to lead us.
Isn't that Resh's job?
Ugh.
When word came of the attack on the Proving,
War-Chief Sona assembled a War Party to give chase.
But in their haste to get vengeance,
some Braves broke rank and raced ahead.
Straight into a trap.
A pack of crazed machines seething with corruption
fell upon the braves and savaged them.
War-Chief Sona led a counter-charge
and destroyed the machines but…
By then the killers were gone and our losses were extreme.
She called for volunteers and went after the killers.
You didn't volunteer?
Of course I did but Sona denied me that.
She ordered me to see the wounded back to the Embrace.
And to guard this gate,
to guard the Embrace, with my life.
That was days ago and since then there's been no word from her.
So there's no way to know if she's alive or dead.
If anyone could survive out there it would be her.
Sona's prowess is legend.
An unbending spear to measure ourselves against.
Sounds like she sets a high standard.
Ugh, you have no idea.
She's my mother.
I should be on my way.
Aloy…!
Before you make the journey to Mother's Crown and beyond.
Is there any chance you could search for Sona?
Where was she last seen?
The War Party massacre site.
A wooded hollow across from Devil's Thirst on this side of the river.
You might be able to pick up her trail there.
She went after the killers who attacked the Proving.
Who killed those we love.
Who tried to kill you…
I get it Varl. I'll see what I can do.
[in the distance]
May the Goddess protect!